<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Random Bits of Knowledge</title>
<link>https://antomon.github.io/collections/cabinet-digital-curiosities.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://antomon.github.io/collections/cabinet-digital-curiosities.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Welcome to the Cabinet of Digital Curiosities, a curated collection of the internet’s most peculiar, delightful, and thought-provoking treasures. From quirky websites and esoteric papers to strange tools and delightful oddities, this is a space to explore the weird, wonderful, and whimsically esoteric corners of the digital world. Whether it’s purely entertaining, surprisingly insightful, or intriguingly useless, each entry is a little spark of curiosity waiting to be discovered. Dive in and let your sense of wonder guide you!</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.27</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>The Egg-stravagant Quest for the Perfect Yolk</title>
  <dc:creator>Antonio Montano</dc:creator>
  <link>https://antomon.github.io/collections/cdcposts/best-cooked-egg/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://antomon.github.io/collections/cdcposts/best-cooked-egg/cooked-egg.webp" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><section id="scientific-article" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="scientific-article">Scientific article</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>Title</strong>: Periodic cooking of eggs</p>
<p><strong>Authors:</strong> Emilia Di Lorenzo, Francesca Romano, Lidia Ciriaco, Nunzia Iaccarino, Luana Izzo, Antonio Randazzo, Pellegrino Musto &amp; Ernesto Di Maio</p>
<p><strong>Abstract</strong>: Egg cooks are challenged by the two-phase structure: albumen and yolk require two cooking temperatures. Separation or a compromise temperature to the detriment of food safety or taste preference are the options. In the present article, we find that it is possible to cook albumen and yolk at two temperatures without separation by using periodic boundary conditions in the energy transport problem. Through mathematical modeling and subsequent simulation, we are able to design the novel cooking method, namely periodic cooking. Comparison with established egg cooking procedures through a plethora of characterization techniques, including Sensory Analysis, Texture Profile Analysis and FT-IR spectroscopy, confirms the different cooking extents and the different variations in protein denaturation with the novel approach. The method not only optimizes egg texture and nutrients, but also holds promise for innovative culinary applications and materials treatment.</p>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s44172-024-00334-w">Link</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="review" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review">Review</h2>
<p>There are those who push the boundaries of human knowledge—exploring the cosmos, unraveling the mysteries of quantum mechanics, or curing disease. And then there are those who, armed with computational fluid dynamics software and a dream, dedicate themselves to solving the age-old conundrum of egg cooking.</p>
<p>Ladies and gentlemen, science has finally done it: periodic egg cooking.</p>
<p>If you ever found yourself lying awake at night, haunted by the knowledge that egg whites and yolks require different cooking temperatures but didn’t want to face the barbarity of cracking an egg into a pan, worry no more. Di Lorenzo et al.&nbsp;have blessed us with a solution so elegantly complex that it makes the Hadron Collider look like a child’s toy.</p>
<section id="methodology-or-how-to-overcomplicate-breakfast" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="methodology-or-how-to-overcomplicate-breakfast">Methodology: or, how to overcomplicate breakfast</h3>
<p>The authors introduce the concept of “periodic boundary conditions”—which, if you assumed was a theory reserved for quantum mechanics, you’d be mistaken. Apparently, the same principles that guide subatomic particles can be applied to your Sunday brunch. By dunking eggs repeatedly in hot and cold water, one achieves the seemingly impossible: a yolk at 67°C and an albumen at 85°C, without separation. Revolutionary. It’s unclear if the process also requires a synchronized swimming routine, but I wouldn’t be surprised.</p>
<p>The team employed a dazzling array of techniques—Sensory Analysis, Texture Profile Analysis, Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance, and High-Resolution Mass Spectrometry. Because, as we all know, breakfast isn’t truly complete without a spectroscopic deep dive into the molecular nuances of your omelet.</p>
</section>
<section id="findings-the-egg-stential-revelation" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="findings-the-egg-stential-revelation">Findings: the egg-stential revelation</h3>
<p>Through meticulous experimentation, the researchers confirm what every Michelin-starred chef and every grandmother with a stovetop has known for centuries: cooking time and temperature affect texture. Astonishing.</p>
<p>But let’s not dismiss their achievement. They have, in fact, demonstrated that by dunking an egg in and out of hot and cold water like some sort of culinary yo-yo, one can optimize both yolk and white consistency. The periodic egg, they argue, surpasses sous vide in its “creaminess factor,” while also maintaining a respectable firmness in the albumen. It’s the Goldilocks zone of egg cookery—neither too runny nor too rubbery.</p>
</section>
<section id="implications-nobel-prize-or-michelin-star" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="implications-nobel-prize-or-michelin-star">Implications: Nobel Prize or Michelin Star?</h3>
<p>Beyond its culinary implications, the paper boldly suggests that this method might have applications beyond the kitchen—perhaps in material science, crystallization, or even curing processes. Who knew that the humble egg could be the Rosetta Stone of thermodynamics? One can only imagine the conversations that will now transpire in industrial research labs: “Before we finalize this polymer’s thermal cycling treatment, let’s check what the egg paper suggests.”</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts-the-yolks-on-us" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts-the-yolks-on-us">Final thoughts: the yolk’s on us</h3>
<p>In all seriousness, while this paper might at first glance seem like a comedic exercise in over-engineering, it does underscore the growing intersection of food science and engineering. It takes a truly curious mind to apply computational modeling to breakfast and an even braver one to defend it in peer review.</p>
<p>Would I try periodic egg cooking at home? Absolutely not. My saucepan and I have an agreement: I provide the heat, it cooks the egg, and we don’t overthink it. But do I admire the effort? Wholeheartedly. It’s a reminder that no matter how trivial a problem may seem, there’s always room for scientific curiosity—and a little bit of egg-centric madness.</p>


</section>
</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>food</category>
  <category>physics</category>
  <category>🇬🇧</category>
  <guid>https://antomon.github.io/collections/cdcposts/best-cooked-egg/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 09 Feb 2025 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://antomon.github.io/collections/cdcposts/best-cooked-egg/cooked-egg.webp" medium="image" type="image/webp"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Phase Behavior of Cacio and Pepe Sauce</title>
  <dc:creator>Antonio Montano</dc:creator>
  <link>https://antomon.github.io/collections/cdcposts/perfect-cacio-pepe/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://antomon.github.io/collections/cdcposts/perfect-cacio-pepe/caciopepephysics.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><section id="scientific-article" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="scientific-article">Scientific article</h2>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p><strong>Title</strong>: Phase Behavior of Cacio and Pepe Sauce</p>
<p><strong>Authors:</strong> G. Bartolucci, D. M. Busiello, M. Ciarchi, A. Corticelli, I. Di Terlizzi, F. Olmeda, D. Revignas, and V. M. Schimmenti</p>
<p><strong>Abstract</strong>: “Pasta alla cacio e pepe” is a traditional Italian dish made with pasta, pecorino cheese, and pepper. Despite its simple ingredient list, achieving the perfect texture and creaminess of the sauce can be challenging. In this study, we systematically explore the phase behavior of Cacio and pepe sauce, focusing on its stability at increasing temperatures for various proportions of cheese, water, and starch. We identify starch concentration as the key factor influencing sauce stability, with direct implications for practical cooking. Specifically, we delineate a regime where starch concentrations below 1% (relative to cheese mass) lead to the formation of system-wide clumps, a condition determining what we term the “Mozzarella Phase” and corresponding to an unpleasant and separated sauce. Additionally, we examine the impact of cheese concentration relative to water at a fixed starch level, observing a lower critical solution temperature that we theoretically rationalized by means of a minimal effective free-energy model. Finally, we present a scientifically optimized recipe based on our findings, enabling a consistently flawless execution of this classic dish.</p>
<p><a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.2501.00536">Link</a></p>
</blockquote>
</section>
<section id="review" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="review">Review</h2>
<p>This paper is proof that no aspect of life is too small to overanalyze with the full force of science. Armed with phase diagrams and free-energy models, the authors have waged war on clumpy pasta sauce—and won. It’s a gloriously nerdy deep dive into the thermodynamics of Italian cuisine, with the bonus of a scientifically engineered <em>Cacio e Pepe</em> recipe for when your inner nonna fails you. A must-read for anyone who’s ever overthought their dinner.</p>
<ul>
<li>The harrowing tale of the “mozzarella phase,” where cheese proteins band together to ruin your meal.<br>
</li>
<li>Why starch is the unsung hero of creamy sauces, and how to wield its powers like a culinary sorcerer.<br>
</li>
<li>How to impress friends with pasta and casual mentions of binodal phase separation.</li>
</ul>
<p>Prepare to be simultaneously amused, educated, and slightly bewildered by this heroic effort to quantify deliciousness.</p>
<p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00536">Check it</a> out yourself and let us know if a Roman would approve of the result!</p>
</section>
<section id="tips" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tips">Tips</h2>
<p>Before applying the scientific method, here are a few tips: <a href="https://www.giallozafferano.com/recipes/Spaghetti-Cacio-e-Pepe-Pecorino-and-black-pepper-spaghetti.html">recipe from Giallo Zafferano</a></p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/eUpzJs-k0Hg?si=nfLP9d0RNpXVDA9-" title="Spaghetti cacio e pepe" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<p>Or a variation of the traditional recipe by an Italian master of the culinary arts, Massimo Bottura.</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Cjoipd3aWhQ?si=hOTVQDZyjLFwL1mG" title="Risotto cacio e pepe secondo Massimo Bottura" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>


</section>

<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>food</category>
  <category>physics</category>
  <category>🇬🇧</category>
  <guid>https://antomon.github.io/collections/cdcposts/perfect-cacio-pepe/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://antomon.github.io/collections/cdcposts/perfect-cacio-pepe/caciopepephysics.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="184" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
