<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Random Bits of Knowledge</title>
<link>https://antomon.github.io/collections/cabinet-digital-curiosities.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://antomon.github.io/collections/cabinet-digital-curiosities.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Welcome to the Cabinet of Digital Curiosities, a curated collection of the internet’s most peculiar, delightful, and thought-provoking treasures. From quirky websites and esoteric papers to strange tools and delightful oddities, this is a space to explore the weird, wonderful, and whimsically esoteric corners of the digital world. Whether it’s purely entertaining, surprisingly insightful, or intriguingly useless, each entry is a little spark of curiosity waiting to be discovered. Dive in and let your sense of wonder guide you!</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.39</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Phase Behavior of Cacio and Pepe Sauce</title>
  <dc:creator>Antonio Montano</dc:creator>
  <link>https://antomon.github.io/collections/posts/perfect-cacio-pepe/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div class="">
<p><img src="https://antomon.github.io/collections/posts/perfect-cacio-pepe/caciopepephysics.png" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div></div><p><strong>Authors:</strong> G. Bartolucci, D. M. Busiello, M. Ciarchi, A. Corticelli, I. Di Terlizzi, F. Olmeda, D. Revignas, and V. M. Schimmenti</p>
<p><strong>Preprint review</strong>: This paper is proof that no aspect of life is too small to overanalyze with the full force of science. Armed with phase diagrams and free-energy models, the authors have waged war on clumpy pasta sauce—and won. It’s a gloriously nerdy deep dive into the thermodynamics of Italian cuisine, with the bonus of a scientifically engineered <em>Cacio e Pepe</em> recipe for when your inner nonna fails you. A must-read for anyone who’s ever overthought their dinner.</p>
<ul>
<li>The harrowing tale of the “mozzarella phase,” where cheese proteins band together to ruin your meal.<br>
</li>
<li>Why starch is the unsung hero of creamy sauces, and how to wield its powers like a culinary sorcerer.<br>
</li>
<li>How to impress friends with pasta and casual mentions of binodal phase separation.</li>
</ul>
<p>Prepare to be simultaneously amused, educated, and slightly bewildered by this heroic effort to quantify deliciousness.</p>
<p>Check it out yourself and let us know if a Roman would approve of the result! 👉 <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00536">URL</a></p>



<a onclick="window.scrollTo(0, 0); return false;" id="quarto-back-to-top"><i class="bi bi-arrow-up"></i> Back to top</a> ]]></description>
  <category>food</category>
  <category>physics</category>
  <category>🇬🇧</category>
  <guid>https://antomon.github.io/collections/posts/perfect-cacio-pepe/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://antomon.github.io/collections/posts/perfect-cacio-pepe/caciopepephysics.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="184" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
